Guide to the Armistead L. Boothe collection, 1920-1983
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Armistead L. Boothe collection
1920-1983
c0168
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
1.0 linear feet 2 boxes
This collection documents the life and career of Armistead Boothe, an Alexandria, Virginia, lawyer, state legislator, and trustee of Colonial Williamsburg.
Boothe, Armistead L.
Box 1
Box 2
Acquisition Information
Donated to George Mason University Libraries before 2008.
Biographical Information
Armistead Lloyd Boothe (1907-1990) was a lawyer and state legislator from Alexandria, Virginia. Boothe attended Episcopal High School, the University of Virginia, and Oxford University as a Rhodes Scholar. He and his wife, Elizabeth Peele Boothe, were married in 1934. Boothe served as a Democratic Virginia state legislator from 1948-1963. He was a prominent member of a group of legislators known as the "Young Turks" who opposed the entrenched establishment politicians of Virginia government. As noted in a 1970 news release, "he became perhaps best known for his consistent political fight, from 1954 on, to keep the public schools of the State open" after Virginia threatened to eliminate the mandate for public schools in order to oppose the Supreme Court's Brown vs. Board of Education decision requiring school integration. Boothe also served as a trustee of Colonial Williamsburg. A lifelong Episcopalian, he left politics and the law in 1970 to serve as the Director of Development at Virginia Theological Seminary in Alexandria. Boothe died in 1990.
Bibliography
Smith, Douglas. " 'When Reason Collides with Prejudice': Armistead Lloyd Boothe and the Politics of Desegregation in Northern Virginia, 1948-1963." The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, 102:1. Jan, 1994, 5-46. http://www.jstor.org/stable/4249409.
Scope and Contents note
The collection documents the life and political career of Armistead L. Boothe from his school days in Alexandria, Virginia, in the early 1920s to his role as Director of Development at Virginia Theological Seminary in the 1970s and his retirement in the late 1970s and early 1980s. Included are certificates, a few photos, and a letter from Boothe's time as a student at Episcopal High School and the University of Virginia, travel and bank documents from his time in England in the 1920s and 1930s, and newspaper articles, speeches and writings, press releases, campaign materials, and correspondence from his days as a lawyer, politician, and director of development at Virginia Theological Seminary. Of particular interest is a letter from 1969 to the parents of Mary Jo Kopechne, who was killed in the accident at Chappaquiddick in Ted Kennedy's car. Also included in the collection are Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia briefs dating from the 1940s to the 1960s, as well as correspondence, agendas, news articles, etc, from Boothe's role as a trustee of Colonial Williamsburg.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Related Material
The University of Virginia's Special Collections holds additional
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the order in which it was received. Photos and travel/school documents were grouped together by the processing archivist.
Index Terms
Persons:
Boothe, Armistead L.; Boothe, Armistead L.
Geographical Names:
Virginia--Politics and government--20th century.
Contents List
- Colonial Williamsburg correspondence, news articles etc., 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Speeches, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Virginia Theological Seminary job correspondence, speeches, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Virginia Theological Seminary correspondence, press releases, news coverage, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Articles, 1964-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles, speeches, correspondence, 1953-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, articles, Virginia plan 6, public schools, 1954-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 8th District Prince William presidential delegates, articles, button, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Articles, notes,speeches, 1955-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- News articles, writings, etc. on public school funding desegregation, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- News articles, political campaign, "Civil Rights in Virginia" correspondence, 1949-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Episcopal High School of Virginia certificates, school-era letter, 1922-1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia briefs, "The Adequacy of the Virginia Constitution of 1902", 1930s-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia briefs, 1930s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs, c1910s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Travel documents: passports, tickets, invoices from UK, etc., 1920s-1930s (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Government/Virginia related documents (onionskin), c1990s (Box 2, Folder 7)
- School Certificates and memorabilia, Gardiner Boothe documents, 1926-1950s (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Bank documents, 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Questionnaire to Virginia General Assembly, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Agenda and seating for Queen Mother's visit to Williamsburg, c1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 11)